<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Sir Iohn Hothams resolution presented to the King's most excellent majesty, at Beverley in the county of Yorkshire, on Tuesday the 12. of Iuly, 1642. Wherein is manifested his earnest desire both to expresse himselfe a loyall subject to His Majesty, and a faithfull servant to the Parliament. VVhereunto is annexed joyfull newes from Newcastle. Wherein is declared how the colliers resisted the Earle of Newcastle, and the cavaleeres, pul'd downe the fort which the said Earle had built, and beat him and his followers out of the county. Ordered that this be printed, and published. John Browne, Cler. Parl.</title>
            <author>Hotham, John, Sir, d. 1645 Jan. 2.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86596</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2909</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E155_18</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R22163</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99871624</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99871624</idno>
            <idno type="VID">156860</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86596)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 156860)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 27:E155[18])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Sir Iohn Hothams resolution presented to the King's most excellent majesty, at Beverley in the county of Yorkshire, on Tuesday the 12. of Iuly, 1642. Wherein is manifested his earnest desire both to expresse himselfe a loyall subject to His Majesty, and a faithfull servant to the Parliament. VVhereunto is annexed joyfull newes from Newcastle. Wherein is declared how the colliers resisted the Earle of Newcastle, and the cavaleeres, pul'd downe the fort which the said Earle had built, and beat him and his followers out of the county. Ordered that this be printed, and published. John Browne, Cler. Parl.</title>
                  <author>Hotham, John, Sir, d. 1645 Jan. 2.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for I. Horton,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Iuly 16. 1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Signatures : A4.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hotham, John, --  Sir, d. 1645 Jan. 2.</term>
               <term>Newcastle, William Cavendish, --  Duke of, 1592-1676.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:156860:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 19 -->
            <p>SIR Iohn Hothams RESOLVTION Preſented to the Kings moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Majeſty, at <hi>Beverley</hi> in the County of <hi>Yorkeſhire,</hi> on Tueſday the 12. of <hi>Iuly,</hi> 1642.</p>
            <p>Wherein is manifeſted his earneſt deſire both to expreſſe himſelfe a Loyall Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to his Majeſty, and a faithfull Servant to the Parliament.</p>
            <p>VVhereunto is Annexed Joyfull Newes from NEW CASTLE.</p>
            <p>Wherein is declared how the Colliers reſiſted the Earle of <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> and the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valeeres, pul'd downe the Fort which the ſaid Earle had built, and beat him and his followers out of the County.</p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="license">
                        <p>Ordered that this be Printed, and pub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liſhed.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>John Browne, Cler. Parl.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London</hi> Printed, For <hi>I. Horton, Iuly</hi> 16. 1642.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="summary_of_letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:156860:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 20 -->
            <head>Exceeding Joyfull Newes from <hi>HULL</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here was a Letter read in the Houſe of Commons, which came from Sir <hi>Iohn Hotham,</hi> importing that a halfe Moone being raiſing peere the Town (as concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by his Majeſties dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction) which would have much annoyed and hindered all proviſion that ſhould have come by Sea; that hee ſent Sir <hi>Iohn Meldram</hi> out with 500 men, to hinder the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings therein; Vpon the ne<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re approach of whom the Pioners and Work men ran all away, leaving the ſaid work unperfected, which he hath demoliſhed, and therein they tooke toe Lord <hi>Faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conbridge,</hi> 4. pieces of Braſſe Ordnance, and 20<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Cavaleers, deſiring the Houſes pleaſure to bee knowne therein, whether they ſhould be ſent up <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o London or no, which tooke the houſes up ſome <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ime in conſideration thereof, of what moſt expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ienſt to be done.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:156860:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 20 -->
            <head>Sir <hi>John Hothams</hi> Reſolution, preſented to his Majeſty at <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verley</hi> in <hi>Yorkeſhire,</hi> on <date>
                  <hi>Tueſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, July</hi> the 12. 1642.</date>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ir <hi>Iohn Hotham,</hi> ſeeing his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties anger did ſo farre ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing would ſatisfie but his Life, withall conſidering the great miſery that the Towne of <hi>Hull,</hi> and all the Kingdome ſhould ſuffer, if this Warre begunne, ſhould continue, to prevent which he reſolved to become a ſacrafice and to looſe his owne Life to ſecure the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, but this reſolution was at end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb facs="tcp:156860:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 21 -->with a ſecond determination, for calling to mind the great truſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to him by the great Couo<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ell of the Kingdome, on the faithfull per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of the which, the ſafety of the King and Kingdome ſolely conſiſts, the peaceable injoyment of our conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and Religion, the propriety of the Subject, and all that happy Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty which is either wiſhed or hoped for, all which things being ſeriouſly weigh'd in the ballance of conſideration, crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted innumerable cogitations, and doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full determinations, ſcarce knowing in this doubtfull deſigne how to beare himſelfe, at laſt he ſet downe his reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, as followes.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That as he had alwaies bin, ſo he vowed during life to continnue a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and obedient Subject to his Sacred Majeſty.</p>
            <p>And whereas his Majeſty was plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to declare him Traitor, he not fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red but that in a ſhort time, however
<pb facs="tcp:156860:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 21 -->miſconſtruction might cauſe his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty to cenſure of him, that he ſhould ſtand right in his Majeſties ſight, ſince that what he hath done, his Majeſtias Honour, the Kingdomes ſafety, and his owne conſcience did bind him to the performance of the ſaid Service.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That he reſolved as he had begun, ſo to make oood that charge commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to his truſt, with the hazard of his Life and Fortunes.</p>
            <p>Withall intimating the great miſery that was like to fall upon his Majeſty, and his poſterity, by the proſecution of this native Warre, manifeſted in theſe particular reaſons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That this Warre levied by his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty againſt his loving Subjects, will be a meanes to withdraw the Loyall affections of his Majeſties yet truely loving Subjects, when they ſhall ſee the cruelty is uſed againſt this Towne of <hi>Hall,</hi> where the endeavours of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant party has ſo farre prevailed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb facs="tcp:156860:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 22 -->us, that all meanes of ſuccour is taken from us, or any poſſible power or ability to obtaine our liberty, but by imbraceing that liberty, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be demed us. a noble death, ſince tis much better to imbrace a grave in a juſt cauſe, then to live under the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure of an incenſed Prince, ſubject to all that mallice which all our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies can throw upon us, nor would I be ſlacke in imbracing ſuch a deſtiny, did not the common good demand a further Service, which ſince it has pleaſed the high Court of Parliament to commit this charge to me, my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience bearing me witneſſe that I have no private end, nor deſigne, but the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of your Majeſties Honour, the maintenance of Religion, the future eſtabliſhment of a bleſſed and fruitfull peace. and the generall welfare both of your Majeſtie and People, I am reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to bury my ſelfe within theſe walls and to looſe my life in the defence of
<pb facs="tcp:156860:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 22 -->your Majeſty and Parliament, deſiring God ſo to bleſſe and proſper me in my Actions as my intentions are Honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That this domeſtique diſſention would be a great weakening to the Kingdome, and to give advantage to Forraigne Nations, which watch all ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages to get a footing in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That the beginning of a civill Warre, is the firſt ſtep to diſsolution.</p>
            <p>Theſe things truly and ſeriouſly conſidered, I doubt not but that you will draw neare to your Parliament, and confide in them, in whom only reſides your Majeſties ſafety, and your King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes ſecurity.</p>
            <p>This is the reſolution of that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Gentleman, Sir <hi>John Hotham,</hi> who is now in <hi>Hull</hi> beſieged by his Majeſty, whoſe Life the malignant party wholly aimes at, becauſe he ſtands for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the Goſpell, the preſervation
<pb facs="tcp:156860:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 23 -->of his Majeſties Honour, and the juſt Priviledges of Parliament.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <head>Exceeding true Newes from <hi>Newcaſtle.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Earle of <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> having Authority from his Majeſty to plant a Garriſon in the ſaid City, for his Maieſties ſervice, likewiſe by the ſame authority he endeavoured to build a Fort at the mouth of <hi>Tine,</hi> and wanting worke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, he and ſome other Cavaleers for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the pore Colliers to worke while they ſtood over them, uſing them very rigoruſly, thus they continued till they had finiſhed their worke, then diſcharg'd them with little or no ſatisfaction, the Colliers being vexed that they were ſo abuſed, gathered themſelves together, and in the night ſurpriſed the Cavaleers, beare downe the Fort, and made the ſaid Earle with his valiant followers, poſt from <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> to <hi>Yorke,</hi> there to tell newes of their pittifull uſage.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
